Okay, so let's just talk about a couple of
additional quantitative risk analysis
tools that you just
need to be aware of, you
don't need to know in
a huge amount of detail.
The first one though, Monte Carlo
analysis.
Now, this was actually covered in a prior
video, so I'm not going to go through this
in a huge amount of
detail, but just as a reminder,
Montecalo then is a random
iterative computer model, right?
This is basically a whole series of
probability distributions, right?
So when we had the optimistic,
most likely pessimistic, right,
we may have many, like hundreds of them,
thousands of them even, right,
across all of our different activities.
And so we plug all of those
numbers into a Monte Carlo
analysis and you may
come up with a graph like this.
And basically, what this
is showing, right, on the, on
the y-axis, you've got the
probability on the x-axis.
In this case, you've got timeline.
It could be cost, you
know, it could be any
other factor, but let's
just look at timeline.
And just based on this end, you can
determine the probability of, you know,
when we think this project
should finish based on all
these probability distribution
that we've identified.
So, again, you know, it's exactly the same
graph that we saw in the previous video.
But essentially, what's the probability of
this project finishing by week 22?
Right.
Well, when we look at week 22, well,
it's less than 25% probability, right?
About 23% maybe probability of this
project finishing by week 22.
Is that high level of confidence for us,
right?
All right, there's a, you know,
23% probability finishing by week 22.
No, right, we're not going to set our
timeline, our deadline for week 22.
So it looks highly unlikely.
It's only 23% probability.
So we're going to be looking at more
towards the 80, 85%.
Right, so the 85% probability is around 24
and a half weeks.
So that's what we really what should,
where we should be looking, right?
24 to 25 weeks right that's a kind of like
deadline kind of timeline we should be
looking at for finishing this project
right 85% probability right that's that's
a much higher
confidence level that we will
have right compared to obviously the 23%.
Now another tool then is this one called a
sensitivity analysis again you don't need
to know a huge amount of detail you just
need the very very high level basics but
sensitivity analysis is
basically showing which
variables have the great
impact on the project.
And in this case, variables
meaning risk, which
risks have the greatest
impact on the project?
And the results of the sensitivity
analysis can be shown as a tornado diagram.
So here's a very simple example of a
tornado diagram, and just by looking at
it, it's pretty obvious why it's called a
tornado diagram.
Now let me just ask you guys a very simple
question, right?
If I asked you, looking at this diagram,
right, you've got all these risks listed
on the left and side,
which of these risks is
going to have the greatest
impact on the project?
And actually, most of you will go with the
risk one.
And that's exactly it.
That's really about as much interpretation
as you need.
Basically, it's showing you've got all
these risks, remember, sensitivity is
showing which variables have the greatest
impact on the project.
and variables in this case meaning risks
which risks have the greatest impact so
here are these you know some of these
risks or these could be risk categories
right and then you've got the impact on
the x-axis here right and then wherever
the biggest bar is that's going to show
the greatest impact right on the right on
the right hand side are positive risks on
the left-hand side are negative risks
right and whatever is the biggest you know
whichever of these risks have the biggest
bar that's the one that's going to show
the have the greatest impact on on on your
project, really about as much interpretation
as you need for the P&P exam on this.
And then another minor tool that,
again, you just need to be aware of for
quantitative analysis is this one called
the influence diagram.
And what an influence diagram
is, is showing an outcome
and all the factors that
could lead to that outcome.
And what the relationship is between each
other, between each of these factors.
So just, again, as a very, very high-level
simple example.
What's the outcome here?
The outcome, stopping distance.
What is going to cause an increase in
stopping distance?
Well, you've got all these factors,
right?
Thinking distance is increased,
breaking distance is increased.
What increases a breaking distance?
Well, all of these factors.
Increasing speed, massive vehicle,
poor road conditions, poor car conditions,
like bad tires, that kind of thing.
What's going to increase thinking distance
of the driver?
Well, these factors.
Tiredness, increasing speed, DUI,
other types of distractions.
So collectively, all of these are going to
influence the thinking distance,
which is going to influence stopping
distance.
And that's really what an influence
diagram is.
So it's looking at an outcome,
this is the outcome, looking at all of the
different factors and
the relationship between
each factor that can lead to the outcome.
So these are just some of
the additional minor tools you
should be aware of when it
comes to quantitative risk analysis.